Finding Aid for Old West Side Association records, 1966-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Old West Side Association records 1966-1978
Old West Side Association, inc.
0.5 linear feet
93815 Bm 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan neighborhood association established to preserve the architectural character of homes in historically designated area of the city. Background information on the organization, correspondence, and topical file detailing activities of the organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Yvonne Wulff (Donor No. 5206 ) in February 1992.
The record group is open to research.
The Old West Side Association was formed in 1966 after developers attempted the construction of a high-rise apartment building in the Old West Side of Ann Arbor. The threat of increased taxes, lack of contact with the families in this multi-family unit, increased traffic, and the incongruity of the modern architecture led concerned residents to approach the Ann Arbor City council.
Represented by landscape architect Clarence Roy, Art Professor Chet LaMore of the University of Michigan, and then Fourth Ward Councilman, John Hathaway, negotiations with the city council successfully blocked the construction proposal.
Since that time the Association has been awarded a grant from the National Trust for Historic Preservation enabling it to compile an environmental survey of the neighborhood, complete with recommendations for action.
The records of the Old West Side Association document the founding and subsequent growth of a neighborhood group in Ann Arbor, Michigan organized to preserve the historic architecture of their neighborhood. The record group has been divided into three series: Background Materials, Correspondence, and a Topical File.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Historic districts--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Homeowners' associations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Old West Side Association, inc.; Old West Side (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- Background Materials, 1967-1970
  Background Materials (1967-1970) contains a chronology of Old West Side activities and publications from 1967 to 1970. A newspaper article, resolution and an outline for the physical improvement of a neighborhood also provide important information about the objectives of this organization.
  - 1966-1970 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1966-1974
  Correspondence (1966-1974) contains letters written by Clarence Roy regarding the initial protest of residents to the proposed building of a high-rise apartment building on the Old West Side, neighborhood preservation and rehabilitation, and reaction from neighborhood homeowners and Ann Arbor city officials.
  - 1966-March 1970 (Box 1)
  - June-December 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1971 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1972 (Box 1)
  - March-June 1972 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
- Topical File
  A Topical File (1966-1978) includes bylaws of the Old West Side Association, a final report of the Old West Side Historic District Study Committee, and material documenting city councilman John Hathaway's participation in the Association. Also included are maps covering every square block of the Old West Side.
  - Bylaws, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Historic District, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Hathaway, John R. (Box 1)
  - Maps (Box 1)